Albany Jewish Community; Collection mss037
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Albany, New York Jewish Community Collection
1905-1990
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Greater Albany Jewish Federation
mss037
2.03 cubic ft.
The Jewish Community of the Albany, New York area is featured in the Collection which was brought together to show community involvement in the region by the Greater Albany Jewish Federation and the University Libraries of the University at Albany, SUNY. This collection contains photographs, meeting minutes, commemoration papers, local area newspapers, academic articles, community reports, and a prayer book.
Access
Access to these records is unrestricted with the exception of one folder marked on the inventory.
Acquisition Information
This is an organically assembled collection initially brought together by the Greater Albany Jewish Federation and the University Libraries of the University at Albany, SUNY in the late 1970s and early 1980s.
Biographical Sketch
According to The Jews in Albany, New York by Louis Silver, the first Jewish settlers in the fast growing commercial center that became Albany arrived in the mid-1650s. This small community declined as trade diminished during the late 17th century and there was no organized Jewish community in the area during the 18th Century. As trade and immigration from Central Europe to Albany flourished during the early 19th century, the Jewish population increased and Albany's first synagogue was dedicated in 1841. Eastern European Jews, predominantly Poles and Russians, began immigrating to Albany in the mid- to late-19th century. As a direct result of this influx of newcomers, Silver cites the Jewish population in Albany in 1886 as being approximately 3,000. By the turn of the 20th century, this number reached 4,000 and continued to grow. According to Henry Brownstein, in Being Jewish in Albany, New York: Origins and Manifestations of Diversity, the Jewish population in Albany was around 13,500 by the late 1970s.
Throughout the 19th and 20th centuries, Jews in Albany created additional synagogues along with fraternal and philanthropic organizations. This included a local chapter of B'nai B'rith, a home for the aged, a women's benevolent society, the Jewish Community Center, a YMHA and YWHA and more. An organized Jewish labor movement also began in earnest in the 1890s.
The Greater Albany Jewish Federation was originally called the Albany Jewish Community Council when it was established in 1952. It was renamed the Greater Albany Jewish Federation in 1978. It was again renamed in 1986 to the United Jewish Federation of Northeastern New York after it merged with other Jewish organizations in the region. It is a non-profit organization whose mission is to serve the Jewish community in the region.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents Jewish life in the Greater Albany area of New York and consists of two series: Series 1: Subject Files, Series 2: Photographs. Series 1 contains the meeting minutes of the Congregation of Beth El Jacob from 1957-1961, local area Jewish newspapers, newspaper clippings, mortgage files, various local area Jewish organizations’ anniversary commemoration pamphlets, community reports, a master list of Soviet Jewish immigrants, and a bound volume of a Jewish prayer book in Yiddish. Series 2 contains photographs and portraits, many taken by Morris Gerber depicting special events, military personnel, and everyday life in the Jewish community between 1926 and 1961.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Subject Files, 1905-1990, Undated
Series 2 - Photographs, 1926-1961, Undated
Both series are arranged alphabetically
Albany, New York; Ethnic Groups; Judaism--New York (State)--Albany; Religious gatherings--New York (State)--Albany; Religious communities--New York (State)--Albany; Fund raising--New York (State)--Albany; Synagogues--New York (State)--Albany; Religious institutions--New York (State)--Albany; Clubs--New York (State)--Albany; Charities--New York (State)--Albany; Community life--New York (State)--Albany; Newspapers; Photographs; Pamphlets; Minutes; Articles; Greater Albany Jewish Federation; B’nai B’rith
- Subject Files, 1905-1990; Undated; 1; 1.43 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1 contains the meeting minutes of the Congregation of Beth El Jacob from 1957-1961, local area Jewish newspapers, newspaper clippings, mortgage files, various local area Jewish organizations’ anniversary commemoration pamphlets, academic articles, community reports, a master list of Soviet Jewish immigrants, and a bound volume of a Jewish prayer book in Yiddish.
  - Adjustment of Soviet Jewish Immigrants in the Albany (N.Y.) Area by Walter P Zenner and Debra Hiller, 1983 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - The Albany Jewish World, 1976; 1979 (Oversized 1, Folder 1)
  - Being Jewish in Albany, New York: Origins and Manifestations of Diversity by Henry H. Brownstein, 1975 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Certificate of Incorporation of the United Brethren Society of Albany, NY, 1905 (Oversized 1, Folder 2)
  - Commemorative Papers – Albany Area Jewish Organizations, 1970; 1983; 1990 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Jewish Communal Survey of Albany, NY, 1947 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Jewish Community Center – Schedule of Classes, 1979 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - The Jews in Albany, New York by Louis Silver, 1954 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Meeting Minutes – Congregation Beth El Jacob’s United Brethren, 1956; 1958-1960 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 7-8)
  - Meeting Minutes – Congregation Beth El Jacob’s United Brethren, 1961 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Mortgage Documents, United Brethren Society, 1939; 1942; 1952; 1960 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Order of Consolidation – Congregation Beth El Jacob and Agudas Achim Congregation (United Brethren Society Cognregation), 1959 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Plaque, Congregation Sons of Abraham, 1931 (Oversized 2)
  - Program, Dedication of Newly Acquired Building for Congregation Sons of Abraham, 1959 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - Program, The Completed New Congregation Sons of Abraham, 1962 (Oversized 1, Folder 3)
  - Skull Cap and Prayer Book from the Wedding of Libby Jochnowitz and Behzad Khajehzadeh, 1978 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - Shas Tehine, Undated (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Soviet Jewish Immigrants Master List-[RESTRICTED], 1974-1981 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 15)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Must consult archivist before viewing this material.
  - Times Union Photo Clipping, 1947 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 16)
- Photographs, 1926-1961; 2; 0.6 cubic ft.
  Series 2 contains photographs, many taken by Morris Gerber, which document the Jewish community of the greater Albany area in the early- to mid-Twentieth Century. These include photographs of special events, portraits, military personnel, and everyday life.
  - Events, 1935-1936; 1939 (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 1)
  - Events, 1945; 1947; 1949 (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 2)
  - Events, 1953-1955; 1957-1960 (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 3)
  - Events, Undated (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 4-6)
  - Events – Award Ceremonies, 1957; 1959 (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 7)
  - Events – B’nai B’rith, 1956; 1959 (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 8)
  - Events – Business, 1943; 1953; 1958 (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 9)
  - Events – Business, 1959-1960 (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 10)
  - Events – Business, Undated (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 11)
  - Events – Charity, 1952; 1959; Undated (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 12)
  - Events – Congregation Sons of Abraham, Undated (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 13)
  - Events – Old Philologians, 1945; 1947; Undated (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 14)
  - Events – Temple Beth Emeth, 1938; 1956; 1958; Undated (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 15)
  - Events – Temple Israel, 1926; Undated (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 16)
  - Events – Variety Club, 1950; 1953-1954; 1956-1959 (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 17)
  - Events – Variety Club, Undated (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 18)
  - Events – Women’s Organizations, 1937; 1946; 1951; 1960; Undated (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 19)
  - Everyday Life in Greater Albany, 1927; 1931-1932; 1934-1935 (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 20)
  - Everyday Life in Greater Albany, 1937-1938; 1940-1941 (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 21)
  - Everyday Life in Greater Albany, 1943-1945; 1947; 1950 (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 22)
  - Everyday Life in Greater Albany, 1952-1960 (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 23)
  - Everyday Life in Greater Albany, Undated (Box 2 (2-Photographs), Folder 24-25)
  - Military, 1942-1946; 1949 (Box 3 (2-Photographs), Folder 1)
  - Military, 1953-1954; 1957 (Box 3 (2-Photographs), Folder 2)
  - Military, Undated (Box 3 (2-Photographs), Folder 3)
  - Portraits, 1935; 1937; 1939; 1942-1943 (Box 3 (2-Photographs), Folder 4)
  - Portraits, 1953-1957; 1959 (Box 3 (2-Photographs), Folder 5)
  - Portraits, 1960-1961 (Box 3 (2-Photographs), Folder 6)
  - Portraits, Undated (Box 3 (2-Photographs), Folder 7-8)